<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-mitchell-grow-remove-private-as-02" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Private AS Removal">Private Autonomous System (AS) Removal Requirements</title>
    <author fullname="Jon Mitchell" initials="J." surname="Mitchell">
      <organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
          <city>Redmond</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98052</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Jon.Mitchell@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Dhananjaya Rao" initials="D." surname="Rao">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Dr.</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95134</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dhrao@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	<author fullname="Robert Raszuk" initials="R." surname="Raszuk">
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <email>robert@raszuk.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	
    <date year="2014" />
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>GROW</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>BGP</keyword>
    <keyword>ASNs</keyword>
    <keyword>Private-Use</keyword>
    <keyword>remove-private-as</keyword>
    <keyword>remove-private</keyword>
    <abstract>
	    <t>This document specifies operator's requirements for implementations that remove Private Use Autonomous System (AS) numbers from the AS path of routes sent to external Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) peers.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
	    <t>After the original IANA reservation of Autonomous System Numbers (ASNs) for Private Use was allocated via <xref target="RFC1930" /> implementation specific features were released that removed Autonomous System Numbers (ASNs) from the Border Gateway Protocol AS_PATH attribute.  The details of such implementations were driven by multiple operators use cases and varied accordingly.  At times, implementation differences, mis-understanding of feature behavior and mis-configurations have led to operators leaking Private Use ASNs to the Internet. Since an additional range of Private Use ASNs has been documented in <xref target="RFC6996" /> implementations will likely require update and even more implementation variation is possible.</t>
	    <t>This document captures operator's requirements across various use cases, being cognizant of the operations of current implementations that remove Private Use ASNs, and provides a set of requirements for Private Use ASN removal implementations in the hopes of reducing inconsistencies and variations between implementations.</t>
    </section>
     <section title="Requirements Language">
	     <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.</t>
     </section>
    <section anchor="basicreqs" title="Basic Requirements">
	    <t>An implementation that removes Private Use ASNs MUST provide a configuration option to remove them from both the AS_PATH attribute of <xref target="RFC4271" /> and if Four-Octet AS Support <xref target="RFC6793" /> is present, the AS4_PATH attribute of the route.  This configuration option MUST be configurable at the External Border Gateway Protocol (EBGP) peering session level, i.e. per neighbor, and will impact the as path attributes associated with any NLRI sent to the router to which is configured. 

<!-- Well for Junos and XR the more granular would be per neigbour / per SAFI as AFI/SAFI is nested under it. For IOS which is neighbor centric the above is ok. -->


		The implementation MUST remove all Private Use ASNs from the as path attributes up to the first non-Private Use AS in the as path, except as dictated by <xref target="loopskip" />.  An implementation MAY remove Private Use ASNs from the entire as path (past the first ASN in the as path attributes), however if it does so, it SHOULD provide an operator configurable option to disable this behavior if desired.  The reason for this behavior is that operators would prefer visibility to which network is leaking Private Use ASNs to the global Internet (or any other network) so the behavior can be corrected directly by the upstream network providing connectivity to the Private Use ASN rather than hiding the issue, which may not fully correct the problem if the downstream network has multiple providers.</t>
		
<!-- Ok. Should we make a statement here about which should be the default behaviour ? I guess the last one only. Also we may summarise all options discussed and provide recommended default in a new section all together -->		
		
    </section>
    <section anchor="loopskip" title="Loop Prevention when using Private Use ASN Removal">
	    <t>Implementations of the Private Use ASN removal feature SHOULD provide basic loop prevention to prevent a dual-homed network utilizing a Private Use ASN which connects to a single ASN from receiving an update with it's own (Private) ASN removed that was sent back to the non-originating connection if the ASN to which it is connected has configured the feature towards it's other location. 
		The implementation should validate that the peer ASN does not appear in the as path prior to removing Private ASNs from the path.  If the peer as does appear, the Private Use removal feature should not manipulate the path.  Otherwise, due to the standard BGP path selection process described in Section 9.1.2.2 of <xref target="RFC4271" /> EBGP routes will be preferred over IBGP routes which may have been from within the AS, so without further attribute manipulation, this can pose a risk of a routing information loop to some networks.  Therefore a router SHOULD NOT remove Private Use ASN's from an AS_PATH or AS4_PATH attribute if it encounters the EBGP AS of the neighbor on which it is configured in the AS_PATH or AS4_PATH that would be removed.</t>
		
<!-- While I understand the motivation here I think the above is a little bit too strong :) If we want to go there we need to discuss as-override, allowas-in as well as SOO (Site_of_Origin) knobs and tools. Note also that all of them are applicable these days to most AFI/SAFIs not just to 128. Again this also needs to be listed in defaults section.  

In practice there could be data loops in cases where actually EBGP does not win over IBGP .. it means when MED or Local_Pref chooses to select IBGP path on one of the either ASBRs 

While we are at this you know that some implementations for their own optimizations of update generation vs update replication do not use poison reverse and send back stuff to the clients of RR or RS. Should we sort of separate remote-private-sa in consideration of those two cases .. ie packet coming from EBGP and is chosen as best they readvertised to all members in the update group including the src versus packet coming from IBGP and is send ovber EBGP ? 

--> 
		
    </section>
    <section anchor="noasrestrict" title="Unnecessary Restrictions on Local or Peer AS">
	    <t>Implementations of this feature SHOULD NOT have any unnecessary restrictions on Private Use ASN use on either the local ASN of the router that is configuring the feature or the peer ASN that will be receiving the routes.  Both use cases are prevalent in some networks as Private Use ASN removal features have sometimes been used in network mergers or other situations where masking the Private Use ASN's behind a particular AS, which may also be a Private Use ASN, is necessary to avoid conflict with Private Use ASN's behind the upstream network.  In these cases, as long as both the router with the feature configured and the peer have a unique Private ASN from each other, all routes originated from behind their networks containing Private ASN's can be masked to be their ASN.  In the case where the AS where the feature is configured is a Private Use ASN and the router also has policy configured to prepend the local AS to the as path, an implementation SHOULD NOT remove the ASN's that have been locally prepended as per policy configuration, as it is expected that the local ASN cannot be removed from the path with the feature, and prepending is utilized by operators for various traffic engineering scenarios.</t>
		
<!-- I think this is a good moment to bring the RPL knob I have proposed in XR long time back of replace-as XXX. The behaviour allows to match any occurance of string "XXX" in AS_PATH and replace each of its place with your real AS number. In particular "XXX" can be regex.

That actually has two properties:

- If we have such knob we may actually not need remove-private-as knob all together as just providing few "XXX" string templates (one of them being private-as) as well as allowing for non private "XXX" strings match seems much more general knob to have. Having it part of BGP outbound or inbound policy also makes its use more flexible. 

- Inserting as many local real AS numbers in place of each replaced string match has two nice properities. It honors BGP TE if someone appended N number of given AS to discourage given path from being selected as the best. It also naturally maintains loop free based on AS_PATH paradigm. 

Regardless of replace-as knob should we have an option to instead of blindly deleting also replace each occurance of deleted private AS with given local real AS number ? 

--> 		
		
				
    </section>
    <section anchor="asreplace" title="Private ASN Replacement Alternative">
	    <t>Implementations of this feature MAY include the capability to alternatively replace Private Use ASN's in the AS Path with the local router ASN, thereby maintaining the original as path length when advertising the update to upstream networks.  If this capability exists, it SHOULD NOT be the default behavior of the Private ASN removal feature and therefore MUST be operator configurable.</t>
		
<!-- Exactly :) Just wrote about it above ... --> 
		
		
    </section>
    <section anchor="adjranges" title="Behavior Towards other Special-Use ASNs">
	    <t>Implementations of this feature SHOULD NOT remove Documentation ASNs <xref target="RFC5398" /> as this may encourage their use by operators.  These ASNs are not reserved for Private Use and use of them is likely the result of a misconfiguration.  Due to historical reasons and lack of operator guidance on Last ASNs prior to <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-last-as-reservation" /> implementations MAY remove Last ASNs, which are deployed in some networks as if they are Private Use ASNs, even though this is not recommended to operators for the reasons specified in that document.  If the implementation supports this, the behavior towards Last ASNs SHOULD be consistent with the behavior of the implementation towards Private Use ASNs as specified in this document.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="ops" title="Operational Considerations">
	    <t>It should be noted that removing items from the AS_PATH or AS4_PATH poses some risk and could introduce the chance of a routing loop.  Further operational considerations for the use of Private Use ASNs are documented in <xref target="RFC6996" />.</t>
    </section>
   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
	   <t>There are no IANA actions required by this document.  Current Private Use, Documentation and Last ASN registrations discussed in this document are located in the <xref target="IANA.AS">IANA AS Numbers registry</xref>.</t>
   </section>
   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
	   <t>There are no new security concerns in relation to the feature described in this document.  General BGP security considerations are discussed in <xref target="RFC4271" /> and <xref target="RFC4272" />.  Identification of the originator of a route with a Private Use ASN in the AS path would have to be done by tracking the route back to the neighboring globally unique AS in the path or by inspecting other attributes.</t>
   </section>
   </middle>

   <back>
	   <references title="Normative References">
		   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
		   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271.xml"?>
		   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5398.xml"?>
		   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6793.xml"?>
		   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6996.xml"?>
		   <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-idr-last-as-reservation.xml"?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
	    <reference anchor="IANA.AS" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/as-numbers/">
		    <front>
			    <title>Autonomous System (AS) Numbers</title>
			    <author surname="IANA" fullname="IANA"><organization/></author>
			    <date month="January" year="2014"/>
		    </front>
	    </reference>
		   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1930.xml"?>
		   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4272.xml"?>
    </references>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
	   <t>JM - Placeholder.</t>
   </section>
  </back>

</rfc>

